Guide to the Joseph Urban Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series III: New York
  - Subseries III.4: Ziegfeld Productions, 1915-1932
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1919, June 16, 1919:
      Written by Irving Berlin, Gene Buck, Rennold Wolf and Dave Stamper, ballet by Victor Herbert, costumes by Lucile et al., directed by Ned Wayburn at the New Amsterdam Theater with Eddie Cantor, Johnny and Ray Dooley, Eddie Dowling, Phil Dwyer, the Fairbanks Twins, Mary Hay, George LeMaire, Marilyn Miller, John Steele, Van and Schenck, Hazel Washburn and Bert Williams. 171 performances
      - 1 drawing, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Twilight curtain, 23x33 (22x18) cm., sig. (Box B11, Folder 1)
      - 18 p. sketches and notes (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - 13 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 2)
      - 42 photographs of set drawings (Box 16, Folder 10)
      - Program, 2 p. (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - Caesar's Wife, November 24, 1919:
      Drama in 3 acts by W. Somerset Maugham, directed by B. Iden Payne, starring Billie Burke, Norman Trevor, and Ernest Glendenning at the Liberty Theater. 81 performances.
      - 12 sketches and notes (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 2 photographs of set drawings (Box 16, Folder 11)
      - 5 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 6)
      - 1 check stub showing payment for scenery (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1920, June 22, 1920:
      Music and lyrics by Irving Berlin, Dave Stamper, Gene Buck, Joseph McCarthy, Harry Tierney and Victor Herbert, costumes by Lucile et al., directed by Edward Royce at the New Amsterdam Theater with Ray Dooley, Fannie Brice, W. C. Fields, Charles Winninger, Bernard Granville, John Steel, Mary Eaton, Jack Donahue, Van and Schenck and Moran and Mack. 123 performances.
      - 5 sketches and notes (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - 22 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 3)
      - 2 photographs of set drawing (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - Program, 5 p. (Box 16, Folder 12)
    - James Theater, Columbus, Ohio, 1920-1921:
      - 2 detail sketches (Box 16, Folder 12)
      - 4 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 7)
    - Sally, December 21, 1920:
      Musical comedy in three acts, book by Guy Bolton, lyrics by Clifford Grey, music by Jerome Kern and Victor Herbert, directed and choreographed by Edward Royce at the New Amsterdam Theater with Marilyn Miller, Leon Errol, Mary Hay, Walter Catlett, and Dolores. 570 performances.
      - 5 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 4)
      - 2 sketches (Box 17, Folder 1)
      - 1 photograph of curtain (Box 17, Folder 1)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1921, June 21, 1921:
      Lines and lyrics by Channing Pollock, Gene Buck, Willard Mack, Ralph Spence and Bud De Silva, music by Victor Herbert, Rudolf Friml and Dave Stamper, costumes by James Reynolds, directed by Edward Royce at the Globe Theater with Raymond Hitchcock, Fannie Brice, Van and Schenk, Ray Dooley, Florence O'Denishawn, Charles O'Donnell, W. C. Fields, Mary Eaton and Mitti and Tillio. 119 performances.
      - 5 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Venetian, 26x31 (18x21) cm., sig. (Box B11, Folder 2)
      - --Paris-Bridge over Seine, 26x28 (18x21) cm. (Box B11, Folder 3)
      - --Temple of Colors, 26x31 (20x23) cm., sig. (Box B11, Folder 4)
      - --Princess, Queen of the Night, 21x31 (10x22) cm., sig. (Box B11, Folder 5)
      - --Rose Bower, 25x31 (11x12) cm. (Box B11, Folder 5A)
      - 38 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 5)
      - 2 p. notes and plan (Box 17, Folder 2)
      - 21 photographs of set drawings (Box 17, Folder 2)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1922, June 5, 1922:
      Music by Victor Herbert, Louis A. Hirsch and Dave Stamper, book and lyrics by Ring Lardner, Gene Buck and Ralph Spence, sets by Urban, James Reynolds and Herman Rosse, costumes by James Reynolds, Charles LeMaire, et al., directed and choreographed by Ned Wayburn at the New Amsterdam Theater, with Will Rogers, Michael Fokine, Gallagher and Shean, Lulu McConnell, Andrew Tombes, Evelyn Law, Gilda Gray, Mary Eaton and Jessie Reed. 541 performances.
      - 4 sketches (Box 17, Folder 3)
      - 6 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 6)
      - Program, June 25, 1923 (Box 17, Folder 3)
    - Rose Briar, December 25, 1922:
      Comedy in 3 acts by Booth Tarkington with Billie Burke, Frank Conroy, Allan Dinehart, Julia Hoyt and Florence O'Denishawn at the Empire Theater. 89 performances. 17
      - 4 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 8)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1923, October 20:
      Musical revue in 2 acts, lyrics by Gene Buck, music by Victor Herbert, Rudolph Friml and Dave Stamper, costumes by Ben-Ali Haggin, Tappé, Alice O'Neill, Erté, and James Reynolds, et al., directed and choreographed by Ned Wayburn with Fanny Brice, Eddie Cantor, Bert and Betty Wheeler, Lina Basquette, Ann Pennington, Paul Whiteman Orchestra and Dave Stamper at the New Amsterdam Theater. 333 performances
      - 1 drawing, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Spanish exterior, 26x31 (18x26) cm. (Box B11, Folder 6)
      - American Review of Reviews, p. 405-6 (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Lyrics, 6 p. (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - Curtain samples (Box 17, Folder 5)
      - 2 letters, Urban Studio (Box 17, Folder 6)
      - 65 sketches & notes (Box 17, Folder 5 & 6)
      - 13 technical drawings (Box A1, Folder 16-20)
      - 47 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 9 & 10)
      - Set Models
    - Kid Boots, December 31, 1923:
      Musical comedy in 2 acts by William Anthony McGuire and Otto Harbach, music by Harry Tierney, lyrics by Joseph McCarthy, directed by Edward Royce at the Earl Carroll Theater with Eddie Cantor, Mary Eaton and Jobyna Howland. 479 performances.
      - 3 sketches (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - 1 drawing-watercolor and pencil:
      - --trees, 27x19 cm. (Box 17, Folder 7)
      - Ground plan (Box 14-9-4, Folder 11)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1924, June 24, 1924:
      Musical revue with lyrics by Gene Buck and Joseph J. McCarthy, music by Victor Herbert, Raymond Hubbell, Dave Stamper, Harry Tierney and Dr. Albert Szirmai, dialog by William Anthony McGuire and Will Rogers, costumes by James Reynolds, Charles LeMaire, et al., sets by Joseph Urban and Ludwig Kainer, staged by Julian Mitchell at the New Amsterdam Theater with Will Rogers, Vivienne Segal, Ann Pennington, Lina Basquette, Evelyn Law, Mae Daw and the Tiller Girls. c. 401 performances.
      - 2 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --2 Entrance curtains, pheasants, 16x31 (18x16) cm. (Box B11, Folder 7)
      - 5 sketches (Box 17, Folder 8)
      - 21 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 12)
    - Annie Dear, November 4, 1924:
      Musical comedy in 3 acts from the original Good Gracious, Annabelle (1916), book, music and lyrics by Clare Kummer, interpolations by Sigmund Romberg and Harry Tierney, staged by Edward Royce at the Times Square Theater, with Billie Burke, Marion Green and Ernest Truex. 103 performances.
      - Rough sketch of hotel scene, watercolor (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - 8 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Curtain A, 26x31 cm. (Box B11, Folder 8)
      - --Curtain B, not used, 27x34 cm. (Box B11, Folder 9)
      - --Curtain, bouquet, not used, 26x31 cm. (Box B11, Folder 10)
      - --Hotel Lobby, rough drawing, 15x19 cm. (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - --Hotel lobby, 27x35 cm. (Box B12, Folder 1)
      - --Hotel lobby drop, 26x31 cm. (Box B12, Folder 2)
      - --Kitchen scene, 27x35 cm. (Box B12, Folder 3)
      - --Kitchen Garden, 27x35 cm. (Box B12, Folder 4)
      - --Park scene, garden, night, 26x31 cm. (Box B12, Folder 5)
      - Detail for Rainbow Garden and curtain (Box 17, Folder 9)
      - 12 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 13)
      - Set model
    - Louie the 14th, March 3, 1925:
      Musical play from the German, adaptation and lyrics by Arthur Wimperis, music by Sigmund Romberg, sets in collaboration with Gretl Urban and Karl Koeck, directed by Edward Royce with Leon Errol, Ethel Shutta, Doris Patson, and Henry Fender at the Cosmopolitan Theater. 79 performances.
      - 6 drawings-watercolor and pencil:
      - --Act I: Market place, 27x32 (14x23) cm. (Box B31, Folder 5)
      - --Road to Inn, not used, 27x31 (14x23) cm. (Box B12, Folder 6)
      - --Mountain Inn, sig. Karl Koeck, 24x31 (17x23) cm. (Box B12, Folder 7)
      - --Mountain Inn (not used), 27x32 (17x24) cm. (Box B31, Folder 6)
      - --Act II.1: Ballroom detail, 18x36 (14x33) cm. (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - --Act II.2: Garden Scene, sig. Gretl Urban, 27x32 (14x23) cm. (Box B12, Folder 8)
      - Sketches and notes, 11 p. (Box 17, Folder 10)
      - 3 technical drawings (Box B12, Folder 9)
      - 28 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 14)
    - Palm Beach Girl, January 14, 1926:
      Opened as Ziegfeld's Palm Beach Nights, book by Gene Buck and Irving Caesar, music by Rudolph Friml, staged by Ned Wayburn at the Club de Montmartre in Palm Beach with Harry Fender, Mort Downey, Ray Dooley, Claire Luce, Polly Walker, and Paulette Goddard.
      - 2 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Curtain, 26x31 (13x19) cm. (Box B12, Folder 10)
      - --Snow Bound, not used, 27x34 (12x21) cm. (Box B12, Folder 11)
      - --Palm Beach Night, 13x19 (9x12) cm. (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - 14 sketches and notes (Box 17, Folder 11)
      - 20 technical drawings (Box D4, Folder 7)
      - Montmartre Theater proscenium drawing, 37x44 cm. (Box D4, Folder 7)
      - 2 photographs of proscenium (Box 17, Folder 11)
        [See also No Foolin']
    - No Foolin', June 24, 1926:
      Revue in two acts, a revised version of Ziegfeld's Palm Beach Girl, music by Rudolf Friml, written by Gene Buck, Irving Caesar, Ballard MacDonald, J. P. McEvoy and James Hanley, tableaux by Ben Ali Haggin, costumes by John Harkrider, sets by Urban and John Wenger, dances by John Boyle, staged by Walter Wilson and Ed Royce at the Globe Theater with James Barton, Ray Dooley, Polly Walker, Peggy Fears, Paulette Goddard, and Claire Luce. This was essentially the Follies for 1926 but went by several titles including Ziegfeld's American Revue due to a legal dispute with the Erlanger estate over the use of the name. 108 performances.
      - 7 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Portal & Opening, 32x26 cm. (Box B13, Folder 1)
      - --Curtain, 26x31 cm. (Box B13, Folder 2)
      - --Curtain, not used, 26x32 cm. (Box B13, Folder 3)
      - --Cabaret, 26x31 cm. (Box B13, Folder 4)
      - --Oriental, 25x31 cm. (Box B13, Folder 5)
      - --Skyscraper, 26x31 cm. (Box B13, Folder 6)
      - --Pink Gauze, 23x28 cm. (Box B13, Folder 7)
      - See also Palm Beach Girl.
    - Betsy, December 28, 1926.:
      Musical comedy in 2 acts, music by Richard Rodgers, lyrics by Lorenz Hart, book by Irving Caesar & David Freedman, choreographed by Sammy Lee, directed by William Anthony McGuire at the New Amsterdam Theater, with Belle Baker. 39 performances.
      - 1 drawing, watercolor & pencil:
      - --Garden, 26x31 (18x20) cm. (Box B31, Folder 7)
      - 3 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 15)
      - 2 detail rough sketches (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - 1 photograph of set drawing (Box 17, Folder 13)
      - Set model
    - Rio Rita, February 2, 1927:
      Musical comedy in two acts, book by Guy Bolton and Fred Thompson, music and lyrics by Harry Tierney and Joseph McCarthy, choreographed by Albertina Rasch and Sammy Lee, costumes by John Harkrider, directed by John Harwood at the Ziegfeld Theatre with J. Harold Murray, Ethelind Terry, Bert Wheeler, Robert Woolsey and the Albertina Rasch Girls. 494 performances.
      - 10 work sketches (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Sketch of ship deck (Box A7, Folder A)
      - 9 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Curtain B, not used, 26x32 (18x20) cm. (Box B13, Folder 8)
      - --Cactus curtain C, not used, 32x42 (23x33) cm. (Box B13, Folder 9)
      - --Curtain D, not used, 26x31 (19x20) cm. (Box B13, Folder 10)
      - --Spanish Shawl, 26x32 (19x19) cm. (Box B14, Folder 1)
      - --I.1: Inn A, 25x31 (18x20) cm. (Box B14, Folder 2)
      - --Cellar, 26x31 (17x17) cm. (Box B14, Folder 3)
      - --Patio, 32x34 (21x24) cm. (Box B14, Folder 4)
      - --Boat scene, 26x31 (18x21) cm. (Box B14, Folder 5)
      - --Colonial House, 26x31 (18x21) cm. (Box B14, Folder 6)
      - 21 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 16)
      - 12 photographs of sets (Box 17, Folder 14)
      - Set model
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1927, August 16, 1927:
      Musical revue in 2 acts, music and lyrics by Irving Berlin, sketches by Harold Atteridge and Eddie Cantor, costumes by John Harkrider, choreographed by Sammy Lee and Albertina Rasch, produced by Abe Erlanger and Florenz Ziegfeld, directed by Ziegfeld and Zeke Colvan at the New Amsterdam Theater with Eddie Cantor, Andrew Tombes, Claire Luce, Ruth Etting and the Albertina Rasch Girls. 167 performances.
      - Castles in the clouds, watercolor, 34x43 cm. (Box C4, Folder 1)
      - 13 notes and technical drawings (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - 40 technical drawings (Box 14-9-4, Folder 17)
      - 9 photographs of sets (Box 17, Folder 15)
      - Set model
    - Show Boat, December 27, 1927:
      Musical adapted from Edna Ferber's novel, book and lyrics by Oscar Hammerstein II, music by Jerome Kern, costumes by John Harkrider, choreographed by Sammy Lee, directed by Zeke Cohan at the Ziegfeld Theatre with Charles Winninger, Edna May Oliver, Howard Marsh, Norma Terriss, Helen Morgan, Aunt Jemima (Tess Gardell) and Jules Bledsoe. 572 performances.
      - 18 prints of Chicago World's Fair of 1893. (Box D4, Folder 8)
      - 15 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Curtain, 29x46 cm. (Box C4, Folder A)
      - --Curtain, not used, 26x32 (18x27) cm. (Box B14, Folder 7)
      - --Curtain, 22x35 (15x24) cm. (Box B14, Folder 8)
      - --I.1,8: Levee B 26x32 (11x20) cm. (Box B14, Folder 9)
      - --I.2: Pantry A, 26x32 (11x20) cm. (Box B14, Folder 10)
      - ----I.2: Pantry B, 26x32 (12x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 1)
      - --I.3: Outside cabaret, 26x32 (12x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 2)
      - --I.4: Empty Stage, 26x32 (13x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 3)
      - --I.5: Box Office, 26x32 (13x20) cm. (Box B15, Folder 4)
      - --I.7: Upper Deck, 26x32 (12x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 5)
      - --II.2: Kitchen Pantry, 26x32 (14x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 6)
      - --II.5,6: Music hall, 26x32 (12x21) cm. (Box B15, Folder 7)
      - --II.6: Music hall, 26x32 (12x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 8)
      - --II.5,6: Cabaret C, 27x32 (13x19) cm. (Box B15, Folder 9)
      - --Doorway, 26x32 (14x20) cm. (Box B15, Folder 10)
      - 2 detail drawings (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - 15 photos of drawings & models (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - 1 clipping, NY News 1966 (Box 17, Folder 16)
      - Set Models
        [See also Show Boat 1932]
    - Rosalie, January 10, 1928:
      Musical comedy in 2 acts, book by William Anthony McGuire and Guy Bolton, lyrics by P. G. Wodehouse and Ira Gershwin, music by George Gershwin and Sigmund Romberg, costumes by John Harkrider, choreographed by Seymour Felix, directed by McGuire and Florenz Ziegfeld at the New Amsterdam Theater with Frank Morgan, Marilyn Miller, Oliver McLennan, Jack Donahue, Gladys Glad and Helen Forbes. 335 performances.
      - 4 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Curtain, 18x18 cm. (Box B16, Folder 1)
      - --I.1: Palace A, 26x32 (17x23) cm. (Box B16, Folder 2)
      - --Palace B, not used, 32x34 (16x19) cm. (Box B16, Folder 3)
      - --Sleeping Quarters, 26x31 (13x19) cm. (Box B16, Folder 4)
      - 16 sketches (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - 30 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 1)
      - 8 photographs of sets and models (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - 1 program (Box 17, Folder 17)
      - Set models
    - The Three Musketeers, March 13, 1928:
      Musical version in 2 acts of novel by Alexandre Dumas, adapted by William Anthony McGuire, music by Rudolph Friml, lyrics by P. G. Wodehouse and Clifford Grey, choreographed by Albertina Rasch, costumes by John Harkrider, directed by McGuire and Richard Boleslavsky at the Lyric Theater with Vivienne Segal and Dennis King. 318 performances.
      - 37 sketches & notes (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - 34 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 2)
      - 2 cloth samples (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - 8 photographs of sets & set models (Box 18, Folder 1)
      - Set model
    - Whoopee, December 4, 1928:
      Musical comedy in 2 acts and 12 scenes by William Anthony McGuire, based on The Nervous Wreck by Owen Davis, music by Walter Donaldson, lyrics by Gus Kahn, choreographed by Seymour Felix and Tamara Geva, costumes by John Harkrider, directed by McGuire at the New Amsterdam Theater with Eddie Cantor, Ruth Etting, Gladys Glad, Ethel Shutta, Jack Rutherford and Frances Upton. 379 performances.
      - First Act Lay-Out (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Photograph from The Nervous Wreck (Box A7, Folder 1)
      - 2 photographs from The Nervous Wreck (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - 6 rough set sketches (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - 22 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 3)
      - 17 photographs of set drawings (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Program (Box 18, Folder 2)
      - Set models
    - Show Girl, July 2, 1929:
      Musical comedy revue by William Anthony McGuire based on the novel by J. P. McEvoy, music by George Gershwin, lyrics by Ira Gershwin and Gus Kahn, costumes by John Harkrider, choreographed by Bobby Connolly and Albertina Rasch, directed by Zeke Colvan at the Ziegfeld Theater with Ruby Keeler, Jimmie Durante, Lou Clayton, Eddie Jackson, Eddie Foy, Jr. and Duke Ellington and his Cotton Club Orchestra. 111 performances.
      - Drawing of horse, classical style, 20x25 cm. (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 29 sketches & notes (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 81 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 4 & 5)
      - 6 photos of set drawings (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 1 clipping (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - 1 program (Box 18, Folder 3)
      - Set models
    - Simple Simon, February 18, 1930:
      Musical comedy by Ed Wynn and Guy Bolton, music by Richard Rodgers, lyrics by Lorenz Hart, dances by Seymour Felix, directed by Zeke Colvan at the Ziegfeld Theatre with Ed Wynn, Ruth Etting and Harriet Hoctor. 101 performances.
      - 10 detail drawings (Box 18, Folder 4)
      - 47 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 6)
    - Smiles, November 18, 1930:
      A musical comedy in 2 acts by William Anthony McGuire, music by Vincent Youmans, lyrics by Clifford Grey, Harold Adamson and Ring Lardner, choreographed by Ned Wayburn, directed by William Anthony McGuire at the Ziegfeld Theater with Paul Gregory, Fred and Adele Astaire, Larry Adler, Marilyn Miller, and Eddie Foy, Jr. 63 performances.
      - NY Times Magazine article (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - 6 drawings of props (Box 18, Folder 5)
      - 35 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 7)
      - 13 photographs of sets (Box 18, Folder 5)
    - Ziegfeld Follies of 1931, July 1, 1931:
      Music by Harry Revel, Ben Oakland, Dave Stamper, Dimitri Tiomkin, Noel Coward, Nora Bayes, Jimmy Monaco, Chick Endor, Walter Donaldson, and Jay Gorney, sketches by Gene Buck, Mark Hellinger, and J. P. Murray, lyrics by Gene Buck, Joseph McCarthy, Charles Farrell, Mack Gordon, J. P. Murray, Barry Trivers, E. Y. Harburg, Jack Norworth, and Noel Coward, costumes by John Harkrider, dances by Bobby Connolly and Albertina Rasch, directed by Edward C. Lilley at the Ziegfeld Theater with Buck and Bubbles, Ruth Etting, Gladys Glad, Grace Moore, Helen Morgan, Jack Pearl, Albertina Rasch Dancers, Albert Carroll, Hal Leroy, Mitzi Mayfair, and Harry Richman. 164 performances
      - Bridge, watercolor, 34x42 cm. (Box C4, Folder 2)
      - 89 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 8 & 9)
      - 19 technical drawings (Box 18, Folder 6)
      - Set models
    - Hot-Cha! (Laid in Mexico), March 8, 1932:
      Musical comedy in 2 acts by Lew Brown, Ray Henderson, Mark Hellinger and H. S. Kraft, music by Brown and Henderson, staged by Edgar McGregor, dances by Bobby Connolly, directed by Edward Lilley at the Ziegfeld Theater with Bert Lahr, Lupe Velez, Marjorie White, and Buddy Rogers. 119 performances
      - 2 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Train (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - --Mexican Square, 18.5x27 (17x25) cm. (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - 15 technical drawings (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - 59 technical drawings (Box 14-9-5, Folder 10 & 11)
      - 3 photographs of Lahr and Velez (Box 18, Folder 7)
      - Set models
    - Show Boat, May 23 1932:
      See Show Boat, December 27, 1927. Revival at the Casino Theater with Charles Winninger, Edna May Oliver, Dennis King, Norma Terriss, Helen Morgan, Tess Gardell (Aunt Jemima) and Paul Robeson. 36 performances
      - 1 program (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - Subseries III.5: Metropolitan Opera, 1917-1933
    Urban designed several operas a year for the Metropolitan Opera Company during the time when the financier philanthropist Otto Kahn was Chairman of the Board of Directors and Giulio Gatti-Cassazza was the manager. Urban's good friend and fellow Austrian Artur Bodanzky was a conductor, and major singers such as Enrico Caruso, Rosa Ponselle, Maria Jeritza, Giuseppe De Luca, Beniamino Giglio, Ezio Pinza and Fiodr Chaliapin performed on his sets. The productions are arranged in chronological order listed by title, opening date and production information. The last year the set was used is shown in parentheses. The files contain drawings, research material, technical drawings, photographs of sets and some programs. The production information is from the Metropolitan Opera Archives and Seltsam, William H. Metropolitan Opera Annals. New York: W. W. Wilson Co., 1947.
    - Faust, November 17, 1917 (1951):
      Opera in 4 acts and 6 scenes based on the dramatic poem by Goethe, music by Charles Gounod, book by Jules Barbier and Michel Carré, costumes by Joseph Urban, conducted by Pierre Monteux with Giovanni Martinelli as Faust, Geraldine Farrar as Marguerite and Leon Rothier as Mephistopheles.
      - 6 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Study, 23x34 (20x31) cm. (Box B16, Folder 5)
      - --Kermesse, 23x33 (19x35) cm. (Box B16, Folder 6)
      - --Garden, 18x25 (13x21) cm. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - --Church, 23x36 (19x31) cm. (Box B16, Folder 7)
      - --Walpurgisnacht, 22x36 (20x31) cm. (Box B16, Folder 8)
      - 1 ground plan, quick sketch (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - 20 photographs of set drawings. (Box 18, Folder 9)
      - 2 programs, 1918 (Box 18, Folder 9)
        [See also Vienna 1906-07, Boston Opera 1913 and Metropolitan Opera 1923]
    - Saint Elizabeth (Die Legende von der Heiligen Elisabeth), January 3, 1918:
      First American performance of oratorio in a prologue and 4 tableaux, sung in English, music by Franz Liszt, book by Otto Roquette, translated by Constance Bache, costumes by Joseph Urban, directed by Richard Ordynski, conducted by Artur Bodanzky with Florence Easton as St. Elizabeth, Clarence Whitehill as Ludwig and Margarete Matzenauer as Sophie.
      - 1 libretto (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - 3 drawings, watercolor and pencil:
      - --Prologue: Betrothal, 23x35 (19x31) cm. (Box B16, Folder 9)
      - --Ascension, 24x35 (19x31) cm. (Box B16, Folder 10)
      - --Woods, 24x35 (19x32) cm. (Box B16, Folder 11)
      - 10 technical drawings (Box 14-9-6, Folder 1)
      - 12 photographs of set drawings and models (Box 19, Folder 1)
      - 2 programs, 1917 & 1918 (Box 19, Folder 1)
    - Le Prophète, February 7, 1918 (1928):
      Opera in 4 acts and 9 scenes, book by Eugene Scribe, music by Giacomo Meyerbeer, costumes by Joseph Urban, directed by Richard Ordynski, conducted by Artur Bodanzky with Enrico Caruso as Jean of Leyden, Margarete Matzenauer as Fidès, Claudia Muzio as Bertha and Adamo Didur as Count Oberthal.
      - 2 librettos (Box 19, Folder 2)
      - 7 drawings, watercolor and pencil: